Guide to the Refuse & Resist! Records TAM.362
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Refuse & Resist! Records
1986-2008
1987-2001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Refuse & Resist! (Organization)
Coffee, Kevin
TAM.362
27.45 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons, 36 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize flat boxes, 1 cassette box, 3 flat-file folders, and multiple items and files within 5 shared boxes
44 audiocassettes
4 Hi8
8 U-matic
34 VHS
19.57 Megabytes in 723 computer files.
1 websites in 1 archived website
Founded in 1987, Refuse & Resist! (R&R!) was a New York City human rights activist group which organized demonstrations and protests for issues related to prisoner rights, immigrants, and reproductive rights. The organization was active until 2006. The Refuse & Resist! Records (1986-2008) contain material created and collected by the organization in the form of paper files, born-digital files, and audiovisual recordings. These files and recordings provide documentation for the administration of the national office; their state and city chapters; and their Artists' Network and Youth Network. These files include informational booklets, fact sheets, ephemera, press clippings, correspondence, issues of R&R!'s publication Counterattack, as well as recordings and promotional material for events including their National Conference, Resist in Concert!, and National Day of Appreciation for Abortion Providers. The organization's archived website is also in this collection. Material related to the separate activities of R&R!'s Artists Network and Youth Network are almost entirely focused on events and protests related to the Mumia Abu-Jamal death penalty case.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials donated by Kevin Coffee on behalf of Refuse & Resist! in 2006. The accession number associated with this gift is 2007.015.
Appraisal
The following were removed from the collection: 8 cartons, 1 flat oversize box, and 1 rolled tube of duplicate material; commercial/widely available recordings (20 VHS, 1 audiocassette, 3 CDs, and 2 DVDs); and 5 floppy disks and 1 CD-R (TW-TAM-362-2--TW-TAM-362-4, TW-TAM-362-7--TW-TAM-362-9) were deaccessioned after forensic imaging and analysis determined items contained no usable data or damaged.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Arrangement
Organized in four series:
Series I. National Office
Series II. Chapters
Series III. Artists Network
Series IV. Youth Network
File titles within each series are listed in alphabetical order and arranged chronologically within those title groupings.
Historical Note
Established in New York City in 1987, Refuse & Resist! was a human rights activist group founded by Emile de Antonio, Dore Ashton, Dennis Brutus, John Gerassi, William Kunstler, C. Clark Kissinger, Conrad Lynn, Sonia Sanchez, Rev. Fernando Santillana, and other activists. The organization's distinctive logo was created by artist Keith Haring in 1988. The group organized protests and demonstrations for various issues including immigration rights, reproductive freedom, anti-war, police brutality, prisoners' rights, and the death penalty, specifically supporting on a large scale the Mumia Abu-Jamal case. The organization's national office was located in New York City, however, over 30 local chapters were formed at the city and state level at various times in the history of the organization, including Atlanta, Georgia; Chicago, Illinois; Honolulu, Hawaii; Los Angeles, California; Miami, Florida; Philadelphia, Pennsylvania; Milwaukee, Wisconsin; Cleveland, Ohio; New York City and the San Francisco Bay Area. They also formed other groups to support all their causes, including the Artists Network and Youth Network, both heavily involved in protesting the Mumia death penalty case. Refuse & Resist! officially dissolved in 2006.
Custodial History
http://www.refuseandresist.org/ was initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2014 as part of the Civil Rights and Civil Liberties Web Archive. In March 2014, this website was migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing include Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures.
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns. Three digital carriers were forensically imaged, analyzed, and arranged in Forensic Toolkit.
New York University Libraries follow professional standards and best practices when imaging, ingesting, and processing born-digital material in order to maintain the integrity of the content.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
The Refuse & Resist! Records (1986-2008) contain material created and distributed by Refuse & Resist!'s (R&R!) national office as well as their affiliated chapters and networks. This collection documents a human rights organization and the execution of their mission through distributed material, events, and organized protests during the late 1980s through the early 2000s. These records are representative of causes R&R! focused on, specifically anti-war, immigrant rights, reproductive rights, and prisoner rights (especially surrounding the Mumia Abu-Jamal case). This collection contains material created by the national office including promotional ephemera, by-laws, merchandise, and membership forms and mailings. R&R!'s National Council meeting files document discussions surrounding the organization's focus and planning for the coming year dating from 1987 to 2004. Recordings and planning files for R&R!'s Founding Conference in 1987 document the formation of the organization as well as panels and meetings surrounding this formation. Issues of R&R!'s publication Counterattack date from 1987 to 2001 documenting the activities and issues of the organization. Files on the planning and execution of R&R! workshops, talks, organized protests, and panel discussions are also in this collection. Events include a National Day of Protest, National Month of Resistance, and various Mumia Abu-Jamal-related events and protests. A large number of files on R&R!'s Resist in Concert! from 1988 and 1991 include promotional material, planning files, ephemera, notes, and correspondence requesting support and assistance from celebrity artists and musicians. The organization's archived website is also available in this collection: http://www.refuseandresist.org/ dating from 2000 to 2008.
This collection also contains material on United States city and state chapters including individual files accumulated about their activities as well as chapter starter kits and other support material sent from the national office.
R&R!'s Artists Network was a collective of artists who wished to connect with each other through the issues supported by R&R!. This network created their own projects and events including Mumia 911, a national day of art to stop the execution of Mumia Abu-Jamal which included over 100 art events nationwide on September 11, 1999. R&R!'s Youth Network also focused on Mumia Abu-Jamal's case by organizing young people to protest and demonstrate, especially through their Philly Freedom Summer program and Act Your Rage events. This network also was involved in the support of reproductive freedom and police brutality.
Fliers (printed matter); Brochures.; Social justice -- United States.; Printed ephemera.; Posters.; Protest movements -- United States.; Pro-choice movement -- United States.; Prisoners -- Civil rights -- United States.; Death row inmates; Correspondence.; Human rights.; Social movements.; Coffee, Kevin; Abu-Jamal, Mumia; Kissinger, Charles C. (Charles Clark)
- Series I. National Office, 1986-2008; 20.50 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons, 25 manuscript boxes, 3 oversize flat boxes, 1 small flat box, 1 cassette box, 3 flat-file folders, and multiple items and files within 3 shared boxes in various sizes; 1 websites in 1 archived website; 44 audiocassettes; 4 Hi8; 8 U-matic; 34 VHS; 46.34 Megabytes in 2,158 computer files
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material created and distributed by Refuse & Resist!'s (R&R!) national office including administrative files and print material created for distribution to members to support R&R!'s issues which include reproductive freedom, immigration rights, anti-war, and prisoner rights. This series includes issue fact sheets, press clippings, press releases, merchandise, stickers, membership forms, mailings, celebrity correspondence files, and informational brochures and packets. This series also contains a brief R&R! history, founding statement, by-laws, and meeting notes. National Council minutes, agendas and notes dating from 1987 to 2004 representing the discussions and focus of the organization through their yearly meetings. Issues of the publication Counterattack range in date from 1987 to 2001. This series also includes an archived version of R&R!'s website: http://www.refuseandresist.org/ dating from 2000 to 2008.
  Schedules, programs, planning files, and audiovisual recordings of R&R!'s Founding Conference in 1987 are in this series, along with subsequent conferences which took place until 1996. Programs, agendas, and promotional material for R&R!'s Courageous Resister Awards which were frequently given out at the conference date from 1988 to 2004. Digital and paper files related to the planning and execution of workshops, talks, organized protests, demonstrations, and panel discussions are also in this series. R&R! often partnered up with similar organizations to get a wider audience for these events including a National Day of Protest, National Month of Resistance, and many of their Mumia Abu-Jamal related events. R&R!'s participation as vendors at Lollapalooza and Woodstock events during the 1990s is also documented in this series. A significant number of files pertaining to R&R!'s Resist in Concert! are in this series for their 1988 and 1991 events. Files contain promotional material, mailers, ephemera, notes, and correspondence related to celebrity artists and musicians, encouraging their participation. R&R!'s Reproductive Freedom Task Force's involvement in the National Day of Appreciation for Abortion Providers is heavily documented through their announcements, fliers, mailers, posters, press clippings, and meeting notes.
  A significant amount of material in this series documents R&R!'s support of the national movement regarding Mumia Abu-Jamal's case and death sentence, some of which was created by R&R! and some they accumulated from partner organizations. Material includes brochures, fliers, mailers, posters, correspondence, newsletters, fact sheets, writings by R&R! founder C. Clark Kissinger, and resource booklets on Mumia.
  - Annual Report, 1996 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Anti-War -- Harassment of Arab People, 1990-1991 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Anti-War -- Jeff Paterson Organizational Support, Background Material, Poster, 1990-1991 (Box 12, Folder 9, Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Anti-War -- Protest with Image of Iraqi Soldier Projected on Building Press Release and Clippings, June 9, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Anti-War -- GI Resisters, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Anti-War -- War Parade, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Anti-War -- Event Promotional Material, 2001 (Box 12, Folder 5, Box 37, Folder 1)
  - Brief History of Refuse & Resist!'s Work with Other Organizations, September 1988 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Buttons, Stickers, and Templates, undated (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - By-Laws and Founding Statement, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Chant Sheets for Protests, undated (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - C. Clark Kissinger Arrest Case -- Files and Poster, 2000-2001 (Box 12, Folder 15, Box 43, Folder 9)
  - Co-Intel Pro -- Research, 1992-2001 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Contact Lists, circa 1997-2002 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1987-2004 (Box 13, Folder 1-6, Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (Negative Reactions), 1999-2000 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence Lists, 1989-1992 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence -- Allen, Woody, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence -- Atwood, Margaret, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence -- Chumbawumba (Band), 1998 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence -- Clements, Charles / Unitarian Universalist Service Committee, 1983-1988 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence -- D., Chuck, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence -- De Antonio, Emile, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence -- Denny, Reginald, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence -- Finley, Karen, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence -- Fugees (Band), 1996 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence -- Gaines, Reg E., 1996 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence -- Giordano, Virginia, undated (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence -- Glover, Danny, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence -- Hoch, Danny, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence -- hooks, bell, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence -- Jane's Addiction (Band), 1991 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence -- Kennedy, Flo, 1985 (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence -- Kuby, Ron, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence -- Moore, Michael, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence -- Shawn, Wallace, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence -- Sommers, Suzanne, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - Courageous Resister Awards -- Programs, Press Clippings, Notes, 1988-2004 (Box 14, Folder 24-28, Box 15, Folder 1-3)
  - Early and Founding Documents, 1987-1988 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Events -- Justice Rehnquist Boston University Commencement Speech Protest, 1987 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Events -- War on Drug Conference, July 1989 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Events -- The New Blasphemy: A Forum, October 27, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 7, Box 37, Folder 4)
  - Events -- Week of Outrage, November 5-12, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Events -- Promotional Announcements, Fliers, Mailers, 1989-2003 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Events -- Washington Area Clinic Defense Task Force (WACDTF) Forum, February 14, 1990 (Box Shared Tamiment 086, Audiocassette 362.0043)
  - Events -- Bold Impressions for Dangerous Times Week of Activities, March 4-10, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Events -- Lollapalooza, 1991-1995 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Events -- Woodstock, 1991, 1999 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Events -- New Music Seminar, May 1992 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Events -- Liz and Hope on Mohamad's Show, Tape One, June 29, 1992
    - Tape One Audio Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 086, Audiocassette 362.0042)
    - Tape Two Audio Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 086, Audiocassette 362.0044)
  - Events -- National Month of Resistance, October 1995, October 1996 (Box 16, Folder 2-4, Box 37, Folder 3, 6, Flat-file-folder Temp 1)
  - Events -- Make October a Month of Resistance, circa 1995-1996 (Box Shared Tamiment 086, Audiocassette 362.0047)
  - Events -- Refuse & Resist! Concert, October 31, 1996
    - Tape One Video Recording (Box 40, Vhs 362.0064)
    - Tape Two Video Recording (Box 40, Vhs 362.0065)
  - Events -- Seattle, October 4, 1996 (Box 41, Vhs 362.0081)
  - Events -- Photograph Album of Multiple Events, 1996 (Box 16, Folder 5-6)
  - Events -- National Day of Protest, October 22, 1996-October 22, 2001 (Box 16, Folder 7, Box 17, Folder 1, Box 37)
  - Events -- "It's All One Attack" Forum, Atlanta, April 1997 (Box 40, Vhs 362.0058)
  - Events -- "Is There Such a Thing as Reverse Discrimination?", October 17, 1997 (Box 40, Vhs 362.0070)
  - Events -- LA Forum Panel, December 5, 1998 (Box 40, Vhs 362.0057)
  - Events -- Photograph Album, Multiple Events, 1998 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Events -- "Art Police" Panel, January 29, 2000 (Box Shared Tamiment 086, Audiocassette 362.0048)
  - Events -- Protest and Rally Binder Contents, 2000-2001 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Events -- C. Clark Kissinger and Michael Green, January 2001 (Box 41, Vhs 362.0078)
  - Events -- People's Summit Workshop, September 27-28, 2001 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Events -- World Trade Center Forum, October 2001 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Events -- World Economic Forum, January 31-February 5, 2002 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Events -- National Day of Solidarity with Muslim, Arab, and South Asian Immigrants, February 20, 2002
    - Paper Files (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Video Recording (Box 40, Vhs 362.0066)
  - Events -- Stanford, April 15, 2002 (Box 41, Vhs 362.0080)
  - Events -- Police Violence Protest Photographs, undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Events -- Anti Abortion at UHHS, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 086, Audiocassette 362.0045)
  - Events -- Award to Lynne Stewart, undated (Box 41, Vhs 362.0077)
  - Events -- A Conversation with Arnold Mesches, undated (Box 40, Vhs 362.0059)
  - Events -- Repression Workshop, Continued, undated (Box 41, Vhs 362.0082)
  - Events -- Untitled, undated (Box 41, U-matic 362.0090)
  - Executive Committee -- Meetings and Related, 1989-2002 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Flag Burners -- Clippings, Statements, 1988-1991 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Fundraising Solicitation Letters, Brochures, and Reports, 1988-2001 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - General Information Brochures, Fliers, Mailers, Posters, 1987-2003 (Box 17, Folder 12, Box 18, Folder 1, Box 37, Folder 2)
  - Grant Application -- A.J. Muste Foundation, 1998 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Graphics and Logos, 1988-1993, undated (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Graphics and Logos -- Felted Square Containing Keith Haring Logo, circa 1990 (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Immigration -- Day of Challenging "English Only", 1987-1988 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Immigration -- La Resistencia Material, 1987-1997 (Box 18, Folder 5-6)
  - Immigration -- "Illegal" Button Creation, Funding Proposal, Fact Sheets, 1988-1989 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Immigration -- Announcements, Mailers, Fact Sheets, 1988-2003 (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Immigration -- Project Lifeline Research, 1989 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Immigration -- Campaign to Shut Down INS Concentration Camps, 1990 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Immigration -- Coordinadora 96, May 1, 1996 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Immigration -- Census Protest Material, 1990 (Box 19, Folder 4, Box 37, Folder 8)
  - Immigration -- Attacks on Arab and Muslim Immigrants, 2001 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Immigration -- Cartoons, Graphics, Stickers, undated (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Intern Application Form, 2001 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - LA Rebellion Support Project -- Report, 1993 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - Letterhead, Business Cards, undated (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Mandatory AIDS Testing -- Fact Sheets, Protest Forms, 1987 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Member Signatory / Subscriber Forms, A-Z, 1987-1988 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - Member Starter Kits, 1987-1996 (Box 19, Folder 12-13)
  - Member Outreach Mailers Binder, 1996-2001 (Box 19, Folder 14, Box 20, Folder 1-2)
  - Membership -- New Member Packet, 1996-2001 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Membership Outreach Forms, Fliers, Letters, 1986-1999 (Box 20, Folder 4-5)
  - Merchandise -- Balloon, Cloth Patch, Order Forms, Pin, 1994, undated (Box 20, Folder 6-7)
  - Mission Statement, and Questions and Answers about Refuse & Resist!, circa 1993-2001 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Mumia Awareness Week, 1999 (Box 20, Folder 9, Box 21, Folder 1-2)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal -- Children's Crusade Information, 1997 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal -- Comic Book by Seth Tobacman, 1999 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal -- Comic Book on Life of Mumia by Ryan James, 2000 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal -- Comic Strip, 1999 (Box Shared Tamiment 164, Folder 22)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal -- Correspondence, 1992-2002 (Box 21, Folder 6-8)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal -- Correspondence, Negative, 1998-2001 (Box 21, Folder 9-10)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal -- Emergency National Conference to Save Mumia Abu-Jamal, February 19, 2000 (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal -- Event Fliers, Brochures, Mailers, Posters, 1992-2002 (Box 22, Folder 1-2, Box 37, Folder 10, Box 43, Folder 2, Flat-file-folder Temp 1)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal -- Event -- A Day for Mumia Abu-Jamal, May 7, 2000 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal -- Event -- Philadelphia Protest, August 17, 2001 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal -- Fact Sheets #1-18, circa 1992-2001 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal -- Graphics and Stickers, 1995, undated (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal -- A Guide to Mumia Resources, 1997 (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal -- Information Packet Material, January 2001 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal -- Informational Brochures, Fliers, Forms, Article Reprints, Posters, 1995-2001 (Box 22, Folder 9-10, Box 23, Folder 1-3, Box 37, Folder 11, Flat-file-folder Temp 1, Box 43, Folder 8)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal -- Marc Cooper Article and Responses, 2000 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal -- Collectible Vinyl Sound Disc Recorded for Black United Fund for Mumia's Defense, circa 1999 (Box Shared Tamiment 037, Folder 3)
  - Mumia Abu-Jamal -- New York Mumia Coalition Organization, 1995 (Box 23, Folder 5)